Guide to the Almira Brown Taylor Scrapbooks, 1892-1962, bulk 1935-1945 RL.11736
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Almira Brown Taylor scrapbooks
1892-1962, bulk 1935-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Campbell, Almira Taylor, 1920-2016
RL.11736
14.9 Linear Feet
The collection contains five scrapbooks. Four scrapbooks (1-3, and 5) feature literary figures, including authors, poets, playwrights, essayists, and biographers. Scrapbook 4 features celebrities, political figures, and professors. All the scrapbooks primarily contain clippings from newspapers and journals, including articles, poetry, book reviews, obituaries, and editorials. In addition, there are loose scrapbook pages and loose material for creating pages.
Biographical / Historical
Almira Brown Taylor was born on 26 May 1920 in Hyde Park, Massachusetts, the daughter of Arthur Balcom and Mildred Victoria (Fuller) Taylor. She obtained her Associate of Arts degree from Colby Junior College in 1940, her Bachelor of Arts degree from Mount Holyoke College in 1942, and a Bachelor of Science in Library Science from Simmons College in 1943. She worked at the Yale Law School, Mt. Holyoke College, Mt. Hermon School, Stoneleigh Prospect Hill School, and the F. L. Boyden Library at Deerfield Academy. Taylor married Vincent Alexander Douglas Argyle Campbell in 1953. The couple had one daughter, Faith. Taylor died on 12 October 2016.
Source: Almira T. Campbell obituary on Legacy.com, https://www.legacy.com/obituaries/bostonherald/obituary.aspx?n=almira-t-campbell&pid=182181084, accessed 16 May 2019.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Almira Brown Taylor Scrapbooks were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2015.
Collection Overview
The collection contains five scrapbooks. Four scrapbooks (1-3, and 5) feature literary figures of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, including authors and poets, as well as twentieth-century playwrights, essayists, and biographers. Scrapbook 4 features celebrities, political figures, and professors. All the scrapbooks primarily contain clippings from newspapers and journals, including articles, poetry, book reviews, obituaries, and editorials. There are often letters and notes bearing autographs of the authors, some of them purchased by Taylor, or obtained with the assistance of Taylor's mother or her friend, Dorothy Kraus. Unfortunately, many of the autographed items have been removed. Pages often include handwritten or typed lists of works. There are several black-and-white photographs, along with photo postcards, and regular postcards. In addition, there are loose scrapbook pages and loose material for creating pages. Scrapbooks have been disbound for conservation purposes.
Authors, American -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 20th century; Biographers -- United States; Celebrities -- United States -- 20th century; College teachers -- United States -- 20th century; Dramatists, American -- 20th century; Essayists -- United States; Poets, American -- 19th century; Poets, American -- 20th century; Politicians -- United States; Scrapbooks; Campbell, Almira Taylor, 1920-2016; Baskin, Lisa Unger; Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Scrapbook 1 and loose scrapbook pages, 1935-1943
  Scope and Contents
  Scrapbook 1 and the loose scrapbook pages feature literary figures, including authors, poets, and playwrights. Mainly, there are clippings from newspapers and journals, including articles, poetry, book reviews, obituaries, and editorials. There are also letters and notes bearing autographs of the authors, some of them purchased by Taylor. Unfortunately, several of these items have been removed. Pages often include handwritten or typed lists of works. There is one black-and-white photograph.
  Authors include Caroline Dale Snedeker, Armstrong Sperry, Howard Spring, Harriet Beecher Stowe, Booth Tarkington, Jessie Stuart, Genevieve Taggard, Albert Payson Terhune, Jan Struther, William Thackeray, Celia Thaxter, Charles Hanson Towne, Nancy Byrd Turner, Neville Shute, Robert E. Sherwood, Monica Shannon, May Sarton, Sir Walter Scott, and W. Somerset Maugham, among others.
  - Scrapbook 1 cover (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1, pages 1-10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 1, pages 11-20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 1, pages 21-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 1, pages 31-34 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 1, pages 35-38 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 11-20 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 21-28 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 29-30 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 31-32 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 33-42 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 43-52 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 53-62 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, pages 63-68 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook 2, 1926-1960
  Scrapbook 2 is a literary scrapbook, featuring authors and poets. There are primarily clippings from newspapers and journals, including articles, poems, book reviews, book notices, and obituaries. In addition, there are letters and notes autographed by the authors (some have been removed) and typed or handwritten lists of works.
  Authors and poets include Judith Kelly, Rudyard Kipling, Christopher La Farge, Selma Largerlöf, Stephen Leacock, Eiluned Lewis, Elizabeth Foreman Lewis, Vachel Lindsay, Emilie Loring, Betty MacDonald, Archibald MacLeish, Erika Mann, and Walter del la Mare, among others.
  - Scrapbook 2 cover (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 1-6 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 7-8 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 9-18 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 19-20 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 21-22 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 23-32 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 33-34 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 35-38 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 39-40 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 41-48 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 49-50 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 51-52 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 53-54 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 55-56 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 57-62 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 63-64 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook 2, pages 65-68 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Scrapbook 3, 1936-1945
  Scrapbook 3 features literary figures, including authors, editors, poets, and playwrights. Primarily contains clippings from newspapers and journals, including articles, book reviews, and poems. There are a few photo postacards and black-and-white photographs. Also contains letters and notes with autographs of authors, some purchased, many removed from the album. Several autographs were obtained with the help of Taylor's mother. Pages often have handwritten or typed lists of works.
  Authors include Mark Twain, James Ramsey Ullman, Nora Waln, Hugh Seymour Walpole, Booker T. Washington, Mildred Wasson, Carolyn Wells, Edith Wharton, William Allen White, Elinor Whitney, John Greenleaf Whittier, Kate Douglas Wiggin, Thorton Wilder, Ben Ames Williams, Owen Wister, Virginia Woolf, William Wordsworth, Lin Yutang, and Stefan Zweig, among others.
  - Scrapbook 3, cover (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 1-4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 5-6 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 7-14 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 15-16 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 17-22 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 23-24 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 25-32 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 33-34 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 35-44 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 45-54 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 55-62 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 63-64 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 3, pages 65-68 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Scrapbook 4, 1936-1962
  Scrapbook 4 features celebrities, political figures (congressmen and senators, diplomats, cabinet members, U.S. presidents and their wives, and governors), and professors. Primarily contains newspaper ciippings, with articles, book reviews, and obituaries. There are also notes and letters with autographs, many obtained with the assistance of Taylor's mother. In addition, there are typescript lists of books and reviews.
  Figures represented include Lady Astor; the Duchess of Atholl; Bruce Barton; Eduard Benes; H. Styles Bridges; William Jennings Bryan; Francis Peak; William Yandell Elliot; Hugh Gibson; Herbert Hoover; Cordell Hull; Henrik de Kauffmann; Robert M. LaFollette, Jr.; Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr.; Charles Pergler; Frances Perkins; Eleanor Roosevelt; Francis B. Sayre; among others.
  - Scrapbook 4, cover (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 1-6 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 7-8 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 9-14 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 15-16 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 17-22 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 23-24 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 25-34 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 35-36 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 37-38 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 39-48 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 49-58 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 59-68 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 4, pages 69-76 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Scrapbook 5, 1931-1952
  Scrapbook 5 is a literary scrapbook, featuring poets, authors, essayists, and biographers. Primarily contains newspaper and journal clippings, with articles, book reviews, and poems. There are also notes and letters containing autographs. In addition, there are typed and handwritten lists of works and several black-and-white photographs.
  Authors featured include David McCord, Stephen Meader, Cornelia Meigs, Marjorie Medary, Florence Crannell Means, Alice Duer Miller, Caroline Miller, Margaret Mitchell, L. M. Montgomery, William Vaughn Moody, Christopher Morley, Ann Axtell Morris, David Morton, Robert Nathan, A. Edward Newton, E. Phillips Opeenheim, Albert Bigelow Paine, and Edgar Allan Poe, among others.
  - Scrapbook 5, cover (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 1-8 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 9-10 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 11-20 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 21-22 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 23-24 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 25-34 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 35-44 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 45-46 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 47-48 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 49-58 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 59-68 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 69-78 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 5, pages 79-80 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Loose scrapbook material, 1892-1962
  Contains loose material for creating scrapbook pages, including two finished pages that were not placed in a scrapbook. There are newspaper and journal clippings featuring articles, book reviews, and poetry, along with letters and notes with autographs; programs; black-and-white photographs; photo postcards, postcards, and a dust jacket. Many of the letters and notes were addressed to Taylor's mother as well as a friend, Dorothy Kraus, who was chair of the George Foster Peabody Awards committee.
  - Loose material (Box 10, Folder 1-8)
  - Loose material (oversize) (Box 9, Folder 9)